Did
Nardu Horizon Pro Tour winner
cheat to win?  The Pro
Tour just ended,
but it wasn't without
cheating scandals.  Yes,
scandals, in the plural,
which even led
to the complete
disqualification of
one of the players.  But
let's
analyze
the rules and find out
if these players were really
cheating.    Let
's get down to business.
Let's start with this match
between Bart Van Eaton
and Javier Dominguez ,
which is the centerpiece
match of the tour.  For
context: these players are
competing in the 13th of 16
rounds of the second day of the
Pro Tour.  A loss here
would deprive either of
them of a chance of making it
to the
top eight, where
they could win
at least
$10,000.  Now I
will show the recording,
try to notice
the problem.    the
long-term impact
they will have.
Plus, you
're attacking with a 6/6 creature,
which isn't bad,
right?  The main
question: can
you turn it around to
attack again?
Because if you
use all those
resources, yes, "Stress Down"
cycles, but you're
wasting
two turns' time and resources
just to
save Fage.  If you
use all of this
and Bart takes out Fage, you've
effectively lost the
game, almost certainly.
So, the main
problem is that there
shouldn't
be a "Wicked Role" token on Nether Goyf.
Let's figure it out.
At the beginning of the Nether
Goyf clip in Bart's graveyard.
Javier casts Phlage,
Titan of Fire's Fury, and
attempts to deal
three
lethal damage to Goyf
with the ability.
While this ability is on
the stack, Bart plays
Not Dead After All.  Not Dead After All
triggers, which adds an
"instant
spell" type to the
card types in
Bart's graveyard.  This means that
Nether Goyf is now 3/4.  And when
Phlage's ability
triggers, Goyf will survive with
one HP, not go
to the graveyard, and not
get the "Wicked Role
" counter that would give him + 1/+
1. And when the aura
goes to the graveyard,
each opponent
loses one life.
Now, thanks to this
mistake, if you
can call it that,
Bart wins the game,
defeating Javier
2-0 and knocking him out of the
top eight.  It's worth
noting that during
this clip, none of the
players raise
this issue during the
game, nor does the referee
sitting nearby.  This
issue, however, was
raised during the 14th
round, after which the
head judges
conducted an
investigation.  After the
14th round matches were completed,
the judges
announced that Bart
Van Eaton had cheated
during his game,
intentionally breaking
the rules.  Because of this,
Barta
was disqualified from
the tournament, and
Javier's loss was overturned,
awarding him the
victory, which
helped him
reach the
top eight.  So,
according to
Magic rules,
players should
only receive
warnings for violating the game rules.  So
why was Bart
disqualified?  There are
several points
we should consider.
First of all, the Pro Tour is a
professional-
level tournament, and if you
want to learn
more about it, watch
this video.  At the
professional level,
players
are held to the highest
standards in terms of
game quality.  Bart is a seasoned Magic player
,
we'll tell you more about his story
later, and this isn't
his first competitive
tournament.  So, it's logical
to assume that he
knows how
his cards interact, especially
as such an experienced
player.  Everyone
knows that you shouldn't
use "Bolt"
on 2/3 Tarmogoyf.
trying to gain an
advantage from their
actions.  Getting an
extra +1/+1 for
Tarmogoyf is already
an advantage, but this
life-sucking ability
actually helped
Bart win the game.
Later in the same
game, Javier, with three
health,
faces Sheoldred and the
same Tarmogoyf.
Javier is forced
to block and
trade,
remaining with two
health points
due to this vile aura.  And
then he loses
two
health points from a trigger from
Sheoldred.  Again,
the advantage was clearly
gained.  So,
given the facts
available
to the public, the judges
100% made the
right decision.  Don't
forget that the
judges
interviewed both players at the tournament.
And for those who don't know:
Bart has a history
of cheating in
paper MTG and,
frankly, he
should be
disqualified from the
competition.  The biggest
problem with scammers is that
we
only know about the cases
where they were caught.  Did
Bart make up
any other nonsense in the
previous rounds?
We will never
know.    The
next
controversial moment
on the Pro Tour once again
involves Javier
Dominguez and the
2023 Player of the Year, Simon
Nielsen.  This match is the
first round of the
top eight, the
quarterfinals.  Javier
currently leads the round
2-1 and needs just
one more win to
win the series.
Let's move on to
the video.  It's
Javier's fourth turn, and they've
just played The One
Ring.  Simon plays Endurance at the end of
Javier's turn
.  On
Simon's fourth turn, after
banishing The One Ring
with Haywire Mite and
discussing the
number of lives,
Simon plays Solitude.
And with the help of
Sunlanser's second ability, they
choose Javier as the
target.  Do you see a
problem here?  Javier
just cast The
One Ring on
his turn, which
means he has
protection from everything and
Sunlanser can't
target him.  Although Sunlanser
only removes one
energy from Javier, and
it seems like
a small thing,
it actually cost Javier the
game.  Sunlanser says: The
chosen opponent
loses all
counters.  This
player cannot
gain
counters while
Sunlanser remains on the
battlefield.  Since this
ability has triggered
, Javier can no longer
cast Wrath of the
Heavens, as it
no longer gives him
energy counters,
and he cannot destroy
the three creatures that are
closing in on him.
Simon wins this
game and the next,
knocking Javier out of the
tournament.  Many people
immediately grabbed their
pitchforks and accused
Simon of cheating,
but let's
look at the
rules and
see if that's
really the case.  Most
point out that
Simon illegally
targeted Javier, and
note that he
knew about the violation
because he didn't attack with
his creatures and
seemed to be laughing at the
situation.  Even
if it were true
and Simon knew that
Javier should have had
protection from everything,
the responsibility for
this does not lie with
Simon.  There are two
things to
watch out for here, and
both fall
under IPG section 2.1:
game error—
missed triggers.
To clarify: we
have a missed
trigger here, as
The One Ring
says: when a card
enters the battlefield
, if you played it
, you gain protection
from everything until your
next turn.
Trigger abilities
are indicated by the words
"when", "whenever
", and "on".  So, first of all
, how do we
know that Javier
missed his
trigger?  Some would say
that Javier should have
announced this
when The One
Ring came into
play, but that's not the case.
Section 2.1 defines a
missed trigger as a
situation where the
player controlling
an ability does not
demonstrate
awareness of the
trigger's existence until the
moment it would have a
noticeable impact
on the game.  The section below
provides four
examples, and the one we are
interested in is the
fourth: a trigger
ability that affects the
game in an invisible
way.  The controller
must announce the
change before
it
first affects the
visible state of the game.  In
this game, for the first time, the protection
from everything that
the ring provides becomes
relevant precisely when
Simon chooses
Javier as the target of the
Sunlanser ability.  It was at
this point that Javier
would have remembered the
defense ability, and the
game would have rewound
to the moment after
Sunlancer entered the
battlefield, and Simon would have had to
choose
another
Sunlancer ability.  To be
completely
sure that
Simon did not cheat,
we only need to
look at the
last paragraph of the
section on
cheating.  These are all
examples of a
player intentionally
violating the rules of the game,
tournament rules, or
lying.  While this is not an
exhaustive list, it
covers many of the
most common
cases.  One thing that is
noticeably
missing here is not
pointing out
your opponent's missed ability.  This is
never considered
fraud.  Even
if you point out a
missed ability
at a time when it is
beneficial to you.  So,
again, while it
looked mean,
Simon was
not cheating in any way.  And
technically, it was
Javier who broke
the rules here.  But in this
case,
no penalties
needed to be
applied to missed abilities
.  There is one
last situation
we should discuss,
where
Javier and Simon appear again in the
same match.
The situation with Endurance.
During the fifth game, Simon
plays Endurance,
moving
Javier's graveyard to
the bottom of his deck.  When
Javier does this, he
places his deck on the
table, and then Simon
picks it up and is about to
shuffle it.  Javier
yells at him
to stop.  One
comes into play.
No.  Simon, Simon.
Oh, Simon.  No, don't do
that.
No, no, no, no.  It's possible. Oh my
God.  Shuffle.  They
went to the bottom.
Friends, you
can see everything for yourself.
Good.  I have protection
.
Friends, I cannot
emphasize this
enough.
Modern is a very, very
complex format.  That's
right.  And it's hard to tell
whether the deck was
shuffled or not.
But was Simon really
trying to
cheat here?
Absolutely not.  I
believe it was
just an honest mistake
after two
grueling days of playing
Magic.  Shuffling your
opponent's deck
when they give it to you
is what you should be
doing at a
competitive level.
The way Javier
places his deck
in the middle of the table is very
similar to
presenting a deck
for shuffling.  One of the
key things to
note about
fraud rules is
that all three
prerequisites must
be met in order to
consider someone to have committed
fraud.  First:
someone broke a
rule.  Second: they
did it intentionally.
And third: they
tried to gain an
advantage in this
situation.  In this
case, Simon
definitely broke
the rule by accidentally
shuffling his
opponent's deck.  Did
he do it intentionally?  This is
extremely unlikely.
Javier is not only his
teammate in the
tournament, he is also
his friend.  And again
, this definitely
feels like a minor
blunder after two
full days of competing with
Magic.  And finally, did
they try to
take advantage of
this situation?  Well,
shuffling a few
cards into
your opponent's deck when they
should have been at the bottom of the
library
doesn't really give
anyone an advantage.  This
could have benefited
Simon, but it could just as
easily
have helped Javier.
Again, I think
this is just an unfortunate
mistake and a common
violation of the rules of the game.
No fraud.
So, that's all the drama of the
Modern Horizons 3 Pro
Tour.  What do you think?  Did
Bart deserve his
suspension?  As
always, if you
learned something new,
like and
subscribe,
otherwise poor
Javier will
have to play
against a cheater again.  Thanks
for watching,
see you in the
next video.